A lot of investors hold concentrated
positions in individual stocks. This can
happen when you hear Charlie Munger say,
"Diversification is for the no nothing
investor." Without realizing that he's
talking about you, or for other reasons
like being part of a company that went
public and holding on to your stock, or
owning stock in an employer that has
performed so well that it becomes a
large part of your portfolio. In any
case, I don't think people are aware of
how risky individual stocks are. In
aggregate, stocks are probably a bit
safer for long-term investors than many
people think, but individual stocks are
way riskier. And interestingly, this is
especially true for stocks that have
performed well in recent history. I'm
Ben Felix, chief investment officer at
PWL Capital, and I'm going to tell you
why holding a concentrated portfolio of
individual stocks is far more likely to
lead to catastrophic losses than to
life-changing gains.
[Music]
In this video, I'm going to detail just
how risky individual stocks are, which
is something that I suspect most
investors don't appreciate. I'll also
cover how many stocks are needed for a
portfolio to be diversified, and why
it's more than the commonly cited 20 to
30, which is a figure based on outdated
research. This is an important topic
because it is well documented that
individual investors commonly hold
portfolios concentrated in somewhere
between three and seven stocks. A
behavior that is more pronounced for
investors who overweight the unlikely
probability of a big win relative to the
more likely probability of losses. If
that's you, you're going to want to hear
me out. Individual stocks are exposed to
something called idiosyncratic risk.
That is risk specific to that company
like what its CEO happens to tweak. and
it's a type of risk that does not have a
positive expected return. In general,
investors should try to avoid
idiosyncratic risk by diversifying their
portfolios. A broadly diversified
portfolio is primarily exposed to market
risk, which is a risk with a positive
expected return. Diversification reduces
risk without reducing expected return,
which is why it is referred to as the
only free lunch in investing. If
diversification is the only free lunch
in investing, portfolio concentration is
like ordering fugu prepared by an
amateur chef. I'll define a concentrated
portfolio as a portfolio with a single
position that makes up 10% or more of
its holdings, which is a figure based on
one of the papers I'll reference later
in the video. Of course, the most
concentrated position would be holding
one individual stock, and each
individual stock after that makes the
portfolio more diversified. Concentrated
portfolios are problematic because they
allow the idiosyncratic risk, the
uncompensated or random risk of an
individual company to have a meaningful
influence on the outcome of the
portfolio as a whole. That might not be
so bad if most individual stocks
performed really well, but the data on
individual stock returns are sobering.
JP Morgan puts out an occasionally
updated report called The Agony and the
Ecstasy that details the range of
outcomes for individual stock returns.
In the 2021 issue, one of the data
points that jumps out at me is the
frequency of catastrophic losses.
Defined as a 70% decline in price from
peak to trough, which is never recovered
from. 44% of the companies that appeared
in the Russell 3000 index, an index
representing the US stock market from
1980 through 2020, experienced a
catastrophic loss. Some sectors like
energy and information technology, had
even higher frequencies of catastrophic
losses. Let me make sure that's clear
because it is staggering. 44% of the
stocks that appeared in the Russell 3000
index over this period experienced
losses of 70% or more that were never
recovered from. This shouldn't be too
surprising. Capital markets are highly
competitive and they're driven by
creative destruction. Some companies
succeed to the point that they displace
companies that had previously been
successful. And some companies fail or
at least struggle to compete. In
aggregate, stock returns are positive.
But within those positive returns are
lots of losers. Evidence of this is the
fact that despite the incredible
performance of the S&P 500 index as a
whole, hundreds of companies have been
removed from the index over time due to
business distress. The other issue is
that there are more losers than there
are winners. Over the 1980 to 2020
period, 42% of stocks included in the
Russell 3000 had negative absolute
returns. They lost money. 66% trailed
the market and 10% did beat the market
by a cumulative 500% or more over the
full period. They're deemed mega
winners. That is called positive
skewess. Most stocks perform poorly, but
a few do exceptionally well. Many of the
investors holding individual stocks are
overweighting the probability of holding
a mega winner. Some sectors are worse
for skewess than others. 84% of stocks
in the energy sector trailed the market
over this period. 85% in utilities and
73% in information technology. All of
those sectors did still have some big
winners though. Looking at the
distribution of individual stock returns
from 1980 to 2020 visually, we see that
most stocks underperform the market
while a relatively small portion of them
match or beat the market and a few do
exceptionally well. Intuitively, this
positively skewed distribution means
that if you're selecting a small number
of individual stocks for a long-term
portfolio, it's much more likely that
you will pick stocks that underperform
the market than stocks that outperform.
This is one of the reasons that
diversification makes sense in general
and why total market index funds in
particular, which hold all the stocks in
the market, are really hard to beat.
That intuition is detailed in the 2017
paper why indexing works which shows
using a simple model that when the
distribution of returns is positively
skewed randomly selecting a subset of
securities from the index may
dramatically increase the chance of
underperforming the index. This simple
model is validated empirically in the
2023 paper mutual fund performance at
long horizons which finds that the
prefee returns of only 45.2% 2% of
actively managed US equity mutual funds
in the US beat the net of fee returns of
SPY, an S&P 500 ETF over their sample
period. This shows that due to the
skewess in stock returns, active
management, which tends to hold more
concentrated portfolios than the market
index, is at a disadvantage even before
fees and costs are considered. Those
actively managed fund portfolios, while
less diversified than the market, are
much more diversified than many
individual investors. One of the reasons
for this is likely that investors
holding individual stocks think that
they know the companies that they own
and understand the risks and
opportunities that they represent. I
think this speaks to the familiarity
bias where investors are more
comfortable with what they know and the
illusion of control bias where investors
feel like they have some level of
control over the outcome of their
individual stock holdings due to their
knowledge of the company or research
they've done about investing in it. But
the reality is that the factors that
drive underperformance and catastrophic
losses are unpredictable. For example,
the JP Morgan study discusses how things
like commodity price risks that can't be
hedged away, changes in government
policy, deregulation and reeregulation
of industries, foreign competition,
trade policy, and fraud by company
employees are some of the unpredictable
things that have caused past business
failures. These are things that no
matter how well a business is run or how
well you understand it, can blindside
its profitability, leading to a
significant stock price decline or total
company collapse. These declines can
happen quickly and unexpectedly. The
2024 issue of The Agony and the Ecstasy
shows a sample of companies that
experienced catastrophic losses with the
magnitude of the loss on the y-axis and
the maximum monthly rate of decline on
the x-axis. The size of the dots
indicate the market capitalization of
the company after its decline. We see
that many companies of different sizes
have experienced huge losses that
accumulate quickly. I think it's common
for investors to want to hold on to
their losing individual stock positions
until after they have recovered, known
as the disposition effect. But in many
cases, they will continue to decline or
will simply never recover to their
previous high. It's easy to believe that
catastrophic losses can only happen to
companies with weak financials, high
valuations, or within certain sectors.
That they happen across sectors, to
profitable companies, to companies with
moderate debt ratios, and to companies
with reasonable evaluations. Any
business, even a well-run and successful
one, can suffer a catastrophic loss.
Another data point that investors may
use to evaluate whether a catastrophic
loss can happen to their stock is
analyst consensus on whether the stock
is a buy or a sell. Maybe if you only
hold on to stocks that analysts rate as
a buy, you're safe. Incredibly, the vast
majority of catastrophic losers in this
sample were consensus buys or strong
buys prior to their declines. Going back
further in time than the JP Morgan study
and extending to stocks beyond the
Russell 3000 index, the 2018 study, do
stocks outperform Treasury Bills, looks
at all US stocks that existed in the
Center for Research and Security Prices
or Crisp database from 1927 through 2016
and finds overall similar results to the
previously mentioned study. Only 42.6%
of common stocks have a lifetime buy and
hold return that exceeds the return to
holding one-mon treasury bills. This
means that more than half of the time
you are better off holding risk-free
treasury bills than individual stocks.
Only 30.8% of stocks in the sample beat
the value weighted market index, which
is what a total market index fund
represents over their lifetimes. A
figure similar to the JP Morgan study.
And more than half of the stocks in the
sample deliver negative lifetime
returns. This figure is likely worse
than the JP Morgan study due to the fact
that the sample includes all stocks,
including tiny ones, rather than being
cut off at the top 30,000 in the Russell
3000 index. And it extends to the
lifetime of stocks rather than the 1980
to 2020 sample period. The data are
slightly better at the 10-year horizon
with 49.5% of stocks beating Treasury
bills and 37.3% beating the market, but
these are still abysmal numbers
reinforcing the extreme risk of owning
individual stocks. Again, most
individual stocks are losers and some
win big. For what it's worth, the author
of Do Stocks Outperform Treasury Bills
has also co-authored a similar paper
looking at global stock returns and
found the skewess to be even more
extreme. The 2023 study,
underperformance of concentrated stock
positions, uses a set of all US stocks
excluding the smallest stocks from 1926
through 2022, similar to the Russell
3000 index to detail the effects of
concentrated positions in individual
stocks on portfolio performance. The
author finds that the median 10-year US
single stock return in this sample is a
cumulative negative 7.9 percentage
points relative to the capitalization
weighted market portfolio or an
annualized 0.82%. 82 percentage points
in underperformance and that 55% of
individual stocks trail the market at
the decade horizon. The author also
shows how the volatility of a portfolio
changes with an increasing weight in a
concentrated position by modeling
various portfolios consisting of the
market index and an increasing
allocation to an individual stock.
Portfolio volatility is relatively
unaffected by single positions at
weights up to 10%. And increasingly
affected thereafter. The effects are
more pronounced for individual stocks
with higher idiosyncratic volatility.
This is where my earlier suggestion that
a position is concentrated when it makes
up 10% or more of a portfolio comes
from. If you hear all this and think
that nobody would buy a loser stock
since smart investors only pick winners,
the crazy thing from this paper is that
stocks with top 20% performance over the
last 5 years have a median cumulative
return over the following 10 years of
negative 17.8 percentage points relative
to the market. underperforming by an
annualized 1.94 percentage points and
60% of these stocks trail the market.
Observed underperformance of the median
stock in the study applies across all
industry groups and among both the
smallest and largest stocks in the
sample. There are a few important
takeaways from these studies on
individual stock returns. Positive
skewess in individual stock returns
means that you're much more likely to
pick a loser than a winner when
selecting an individual stock. And the
effects of skewess are more extreme at
longer horizons. This means the chances
of being a successful long-term buy and
hold investor with only a few stocks is
increasingly unlikely at longer
horizons. Though, if you do pick the
rare winners, the results can be
extremely positive. Underperformance can
happen quickly, unexpectedly, and
irreversibly. Many stocks not only
underperform the market, but suffer
catastrophic losses that they do not
recover from. To be clear, it is true
that a small number of stocks perform
exceptionally well. It's just hard to
pick them before the fact. Past winners
are more likely to underperform than
outperform in the future. Given the
extreme risk and positive skewess of
individual stock returns, some level of
diversification is likely sensible. But
how much is less clear? Research from
the 1970s and 80s found that a portfolio
of 20 to 40 stocks is sufficient for
diversification because beyond that
point, the risk reduction benefits
diminish. This finding has colored the
beliefs of many investors, but it has a
problem. It assumes that volatility is
the only measure of risk that matters to
investors. I'd argue that what really
matters is the expected distribution of
long-term wealth outcomes. For example,
a more concentrated portfolio has a
small chance of holding the mega winner
and a much larger chance of holding
losers. The difference in wealth
accumulation between the worst and best
concentrated portfolios is going to be
enormous at long horizons. Reducing
volatility is a good thing, but even
small differences in volatilities can
have big impacts on long-term wealth
outcomes. A 2022 study, How many stocks
should you own? Simulates long-term
wealth multiples for portfolios with
varying levels of concentration. The
authors find the 25th and 10th
percentile outcomes, the worst outcomes,
improve dramatically until around 250
stocks are included, and the incremental
benefits of diversification decrease
thereafter. The average portfolio in
their simulations multiplied wealth 19
times on average over 25 years. But an
investor with just 25 stocks had a 1 in
10 chance of receiving less than a 12
times wealth multiple while an investor
with 250 stocks had a 1 in 10 chance of
achieving less than a 17 times multiple
of wealth. Again, the distribution of
returns is tighter for a more
diversified portfolio, meaning that the
worst outcome is less bad and the best
outcome is less good relative to a more
concentrated portfolio. This makes the
choice about how diversified a portfolio
should be a preference more than a
prescription. But I do think it's
important to highlight that when risk is
measured as the variability of terminal
wealth, the diversification benefits of
adding more stocks continues far beyond
20 to 30 holdings. If you are confident
that you can pick winning stocks before
the fact, portfolio concentration can
make sense. But the odds are stacked
against you and the track record of
active management in general leaves much
to be desired. Some investors may be
comfortable with that risk. They may be
willing to accept a wider range of
long-term outcomes, including a good
chance of trailing the market or
suffering a catastrophic loss in
exchange for a smaller chance at extreme
outperformance. This is a preference for
a lotteryike payoff, which is fine, but
it's a risk that needs to be properly
understood. In Do Stocks Outperform
Treasury Bills, the author simulates
long-term returns for 20,000 randomly
selected 5, 25, 50, and 100 stock
portfolios. He finds at the 10-year
horizon that even 100 stock portfolios
outperformed the market only 47.5% of
the time. There are different ways to
interpret that result. One way is that
hey, it was only a little worse than a
coin flip that you would have beaten the
market before costs. The other is that
you had more than a 50% chance of
trailing the market. The nice thing
about total market index funds is that
you know you're going to get the market
return even if you don't know what that
return is going to be. With a more
concentrated portfolio, you're going to
get the market return plus or minus the
active return from portfolio
concentration. The range of outcomes for
that active return will be larger with
increasing portfolio concentration. And
the distribution of outcomes will have
lots of losing portfolios and a few big
winners. Research from Vanguard shows
that fund active share, which is not the
same thing as concentration, but is
related, results in a wider dispersion
of benchmark relative returns for
actively managed portfolios. it really
becomes a question of how confident you
are that the stocks you pick will be
winners rather than losers while keeping
in mind that the distribution of
individual stock returns is kind of
scary. Another important consideration
here is that portfolio concentration may
have asymmetric effects on performance.
The 2022 paper, Fund Concentration, a
magnifier of manager skill, finds that
increasing concentration has a
pronounced positive impact on
performance for outperforming funds. But
the opposite is true for underperforming
funds. And importantly, higher levels of
concentration generally hurt the poorly
performing funds more than it helps the
outperforming funds. If you are
currently holding concentrated positions
in single stocks, there are some
economic and psychological barriers to
diversifying. The biggest economic
barrier is typically taxes. If you own a
stock that increases in value
substantially leading to concentration
in that position, there could be a large
tax bill associated with selling it. In
that case, it's important to consider
that the taxes generally don't go away.
The only thing you control is whether
you pay them now or later. Deferring
taxes can be a good thing, but in this
case, it is being traded off against
taking a large amount of idiosyncratic
risk. There are other strategies like
taxefficiently donating the appreciated
securities that can make sense, but this
decision should be approached carefully.
Another less common economic constraint
is control. Some large shareholders may
need to maintain their position in order
to maintain voting control of the
company. The psychological constraints
include the representativeness bias
where people ignore the types of base
rate probabilities that I've discussed
in this video and assume that their past
experience with a single stock is
indicative of its expected range of
future outcomes. the endowment effect
where people prefer things that they
already own. The status quo bias to
stick with the thing that they're
already doing. And in the case of a
stock that has fallen in price, the
disposition effect. Managing these
biases with respect to diversifying a
single stock position can be
challenging, but I've seen a couple
things that can help. One is imagining
that the amount you have invested in the
stock is in cash and asking yourself if
you would buy the stock today with that
cash. Another is creating a systematic
plan to dollar cost average out of the
concentrated position, avoiding the
psychological impact of one big
decision. Individual stocks are
extremely risky. Most of them
underperform the market. Many of them
have negative long-term returns or
catastrophic losses, and a small number
of them have extremely high returns.
Picking any one stock is more likely to
lead to a bad outcome than a good one.
And counterintuitively, this is even
more pronounced for stocks that have
performed well over the last five years.
The simple answer to overcoming
individual stock risk is
diversification. The extent of
diversification that makes sense depends
on your preferences for skewess, your
conviction in your stock selection
ability, and your willingness to bear
the risk of a wider range of potential
outcomes. Getting out of a single stock
position can have economic and
psychological challenges, but these can
be overcome with thoughtful planning.
Thanks for watching. I'm Ben Felix,
chief investment officer at PWL Capital.
Tell me about your single stock
positions in the comments.